Ciaran Carson papers, circa 1970-2010
Emory University
- Writings by Carson, circa 1970-2009, Series 2; Boxes 8-28, 48-59; OP1-5
  - Translations, 1994-2008, Subseries 2.3; Boxes 18-20, 54-57
    - The Midnight Court, proofs, 23 March 2005 (Box 55, Folder 4)
    - The Táin (2008)
    - The Táin, TS, "First/Second Draft," 25 November 2005 (Box 55, Folder 5)
    - The Táin, TS, 5 December 2005 (Box 55, Folder 6)
    - The Táin, TS, 7 December 2005-15 January 2006 (Box 55, Folder 7)
    - The Táin, TS, 16 January-1 April 2006 (Box 55, Folder 8)
    - The Táin, TS, "1st fair copy," 2 April 2006 [1 of 2] (Box 55, Folder 9)
    - The Táin, TS, "1st fair copy," 2 April 2006 [2 of 2] (Box 55, Folder 10)
    - The Táin, TS, "2nd fair copy," 6 June 2006 [1 of 2] (Box 55, Folder 11)
    - The Táin, TS, "2nd fair copy," 6 June 2006 [1 of 2] (Box 56, Folder 1)
    - The Táin, "Final Version (more or less"), 17 August 2006 [1 of 2] (Box 56, Folder 2)
    - The Táin, "Final Version (more or less"), 17 August 2006 [2 of 2] (Box 56, Folder 3)
    - The Táin, proofs with corrections, 4 July 2007 (Box 56, Folder 4)
    - The Táin, proofs, fair copy, 4 July 2007 [1 of 2] (Box 56, Folder 5)
    - The Táin, proofs, fair copy, 4 July 2007 [2 of 2] (Box 56, Folder 6)
    - Introduction and blurb on Carson, TS, circa September 2006 (Box 56, Folder 7)
    - Blurb by W. S. Merwin, 26 November 2007 (Box 57, Folder 1)
    - "Poems," TS, circa November 2005 (Box 57, Folder 2)
    - Research material, "Bull Stuff," circa 2005 (Box 57, Folder 3)
    - Editorial guidelines for Penguin Books with correspondence, November 2005 - May 2006 (Box 57, Folder 4)
    - The Táin, cover art, 2008 (Box 57, Folder 5)
    - Translations of Gearóid Mac Lochlainn
    - "At the Table," "The Flow," "The Irish-Speaking Mynah," "Rambling "The Storytellers," "Troubles," TS translations from the Irish of Mac Lochlainn; includes photocopy originals and TLS from CC to GM, 4 February 2000 (Box 20, Folder 10)
    - Translations of Peter Hackay and Christopher Whyte for The Yellow Nib
    - "Choosing Land" (Box 57, Folder 6)
    - "An Education of Sorts" (Box 57, Folder 7)
    - "Farkasreti Cemetary, Buda" (Box 57, Folder 8)
    - "Gaugemela" (Box 57, Folder 9)
    - "The Light of Heroism Around Them" (Box 57, Folder 10)
    - "The Polisman" (Box 57, Folder 11)
    - "The Tin" (Box 57, Folder 12)
    - The Yellow Nib, cover art, 2006 (Box 57, Folder 13)
    - Miscellaneous Translations
    - "The Blind man in the Studio," TS translation of Seán Ó Ríordáin [originally filed by Carson with materials from The Lost Explorer] (Box 20, Folder 11)
    - "Claustrophobia," MS translation of Seán Ó Ríordáin [originally filed by Carson with materials from The Lost Explorer] (Box 20, Folder 12)
    - "Fever," TS translation of Seán Ó Ríordáin [originally filed by Carson with materials from The Lost Explorer] (Box 20, Folder 13)
    - "Freedom," TS translation of Seán Ó Ríordáin [originally filed by Carson with materials from The Lost Explorer] (Box 20, Folder 14)
    - "The Head" and "The Smell of Blood", MS and TS translations of Nuala Ni Dhomhnaill with ALS from Ni Dhomhnaill, 8 June 1989 (Box 20, Folder 15)
    - "If I were fire, I'd burn up the world," "Only three things interest me at all," "When Picciolini got back here from France," TS translations of Cecco Angiolieri" (Box 57, Folder 14)
    - "The Lament of Nuala O'Neill for Donegal in the Reign of James I, King of Britain," translation for Pat Craig, 9 July 2005 (Box 57, Folder 15)
    - "Let it Be", TS translation of Nuala Ni Dhomhnaill [1994] (Box 20, Folder 16)
    - "Light," MS translation of Seán Ó Ríordáin [originally filed by Carson with materials from The Lost Explorer] (Box 20, Folder 17)
    - "My Mother's Burial," MS translation of Seán Ó Ríordáin [originally filed by Carson with materials from The Lost Explorer] (Box 20, Folder 18)
    - "The Prologue to The Canterbury Tales," TS, 26 January 2003 (Box 57, Folder 16)
    - "The Question," TS translation of Seán Ó Ríordáin [See Subseries 2.3: Miscellaneous translations, "The Blind man in the Studio"] (Box -, Folder -)
    - "Scribe," from the Early Irish, ascribed to Colm Cille, TS, July 2004 (Box 57, Folder 17)
    - "Swap," TS translation of Seán Ó Ríordáin (Box 57, Folder 18)
    - "The Swing," TS, translation of Liam O. Muirthile's "An Luascán" [published in Poetry 167:1-2 (1995)] (Box 20, Folder 19)
    - "Verses to the Song," TS for recording by Padraigiu Ni Uallachain; with two related letters (Box 20, Folder 20)
    - Assorted translations: MS notes on Barántas, Scotish Arts Council, program, 1995 [Scots Gaelic to English] (Box 20, Folder 21)
    - Irish versions of poems in Breaking News (Box 57, Folder 19)
  - Prose, 1985-2009, Subseries 2.4; Boxes 21-28, 57-59; OP 3-5
    This subseries contains Carson's prose works from 1985-2009. Materials in this series include research notes, drafts, various corrected typescripts, and proof copies of Carson's fiction and autobiographical writings, creative non-fiction, essays, and reviews. Much of this series is comprised of book-length writings, which document the progression of Carson's blurring of the distinction between a long-lined narrative poetry and lyrical prose. Of particular interest are Carson's non-fiction work about traditional music, Last Night's Fun, and the memoir-like (as well as cinematic) evocation of Belfast, The Star Factory, which influenced Carson's genre-bending books Fishing for Amber and Shamrock Tea. This series contains some unpublished works, which are arranged chronologically with other published works, as well as uncollected essays and reviews, many of which were published in major journals.
    - Diarmuid Delargy: Thirteen Etchings (1985) [TS for Diarmuid Delargy, words by Ciaran Carson; conversation with Jamshhid Mirfenderesky]
    - "On Our Shores I," TS (Box 21, Folder 1)
    - "On Our Shores II," TS (Box 21, Folder 1)
    - "Down on Dunseverick Strand," TS (Box 21, Folder 1)
    - "The Stone in the Field," TS (Box 21, Folder 1)
    - "The Tree in the Field," TS (Box 21, Folder 1)
    - "Home," TS (Box 21, Folder 1)
    - "Linnegan's Kitchen I," TS (Box 21, Folder 1)
    - "Linnegan's Kitchen II," TS (Box 21, Folder 1)
    - "Northern Horses," TS (Box 21, Folder 1)
    - "Breda I," TS (Box 21, Folder 1)
    - "Breda II," TS (Box 21, Folder 1)
    - "The Grey," TS (Box 21, Folder 1)
    - "The Dark," TS (Box 21, Folder 1)
    - "Diarmuid Delargy: Thirteen Etchings," (Box 21, Folder 1)
    - Last Night's Fun (1996)
    - Last Night's Fun, research materials, loose drafts, manuscripts [See also Subseries 2.1: Notebooks] (Box 21, Folder 2)
    - Last Night's Fun, "Storyteller 1 or 2" [variant chapter title: "Pigtown"] (Box 21, Folder 3)
    - Last Night's Fun, corrected typescript, pp. 1-122 (Box 21, Folder 4)
    - Last Night's Fun, corrected typescript, pp.123-256 (Box 21, Folder 5)
    - Last Night's Fun, corrected typescript, pp. 2-129 (Box 21, Folder 6)
    - Last Night's Fun, corrected typescript, pp. 130-256 (Box 21, Folder 7)
    - Last Night's Fun, typescript, pp. 1-29 with comments by Tess Gallagher and two ALS from Gallagher, 14 August and 15 August, 1995 (Box 21, Folder 8)
    - Last Night's Fun, typescript, pp. 38-48 with comments by Tess Gallagher (Box 21, Folder 9)
    - Last Night's Fun, typescript, pp. 53-141 with comments by Tess Gallagher and ALS from Gallagher, 25 August 1995 (Box 21, Folder 10)
    - Last Night's Fun, typescript, pp. 145-213 with comments by Tess Gallagher and ALS from Gallagher, 13 September 1995 (Box 21, Folder 11)
    - Last Night's Fun, typescript, pp. 220-256 with comments by Tess Gallagher and TLS from Gallagher, 26 September 1995 (Box 21, Folder 12)
    - "Last Night's Fun," corrected proof piece for Southern Review, Summer 1995 (Box OP3, Folder -)
    - Last Night's Fun, corrected proofs (Box 21, Folder 13)
    - Last Night's Fun, book jacket proofs (Box OP4, Folder -)
    - Last Night's Fun, book jacket (Box 21, Folder 14)
    - The Star Factory (1997)
    - The Star Factory, miscellaneous typescript pages, research materials, notes (Box 22, Folder 1)
    - The Star Factory manuscript notes [See Series 6: Photograph of Tess Gallagher with Carson's daughter, MS on the envelop]
    - The Star Factory, corrected typescript, pp. 1-111 (Box 22, Folder 2)
    - The Star Factory, corrected typescript, pp. 112-226 (Box 22, Folder 3)
    - The Star Factory, corrected typescript, pp. 227-328 (Box 22, Folder 4)
    - The Star Factory, corrected typescript, "Raglan Street" - "O'Neill Street," pp. 1-161 (Box 22, Folder 5)
    - The Star Factory, corrected typescript, "White Star Street" - "McWatter's Bakery," pp. 162-330 (Box 22, Folder 6)
    - The Star Factory, typescript with comments by Tess Gallagher, pp. 1-111 [This version has a different ending than the published version] (Box 22, Folder 7)
    - The Star Factory, typescript with comments by Tess Gallagher, pp. 112-226 (Box 22, Folder 8)
    - The Star Factory, typescript with comments by Tess Gallagher, pp. 227-328 (Box 23, Folder 1)
    - The Star Factory, typescript bibliography / acknowledgements (Box 23, Folder 2)
    - The Star Factory, corrected proofs, pp. 1-98 (Box 23, Folder 3)
    - The Star Factory, corrected proofs, pp. 99-203 (Box 23, Folder 4)
    - The Star Factory, corrected proofs, pp. 204-297 (Box 23, Folder 5)
    - The Star Factory, cover image with TLS from Neil Belton, 13 June 1997 (Box 23, Folder 6)
    - The Star Factory, proof sample for paper trade edition, ALS 9 September 1998 (Box 23, Folder 7)
    - Fishing for Amber (2000)
    - Fishing for Amber, research materials (Box 24, Folder 1)
    - Fishing for Amber, TS "Aborted Version" (Box 24, Folder 2)
    - Fishing for Amber, TS "K" (Box 24, Folder 3)
    - Unidentified fragments, TS from Carson's "First Drafts" folder (Box 24, Folder 4)
    - "Antipodes," MS and TS from Carson's "First Drafts" folder" (Box 24, Folder 5)
    - "Berenice," MS and TS from "First Drafts" from Carson's "First Drafts" folder (Box 24, Folder 6)
    - "Clepsydra," MS and TS from Carson's "First Drafts" folder (Box 24, Folder 7)
    - "Delphinium," TS from Carson's "First Drafts" folder (Box 24, Folder 8)
    - "Ergot," TS from Carson's "First Drafts" folder (Box 24, Folder 9)
    - "Foxglove,"TS from Carson's "First Drafts" folder (Box 24, Folder 10)
    - "Ganymede," MS and TS from Carson's "First Drafts" folder (Box 24, Folder 11)
    - "Helicon" [variant title: "Holland"], MS and TS from Carson's "First Drafts" folder (Box 24, Folder 12)
    - "Io," MS and TS from Carson's "First Drafts" folder (Box 24, Folder 13)
    - "Jacinth," MS and TS from Carson's "First Drafts" folder (Box 24, Folder 14)
    - "Kipper," MS and TS from Carson's "First Drafts" folder (Box 24, Folder 15)
    - "Leyden" [variant title: "Leiden"], TS from Carson's "First Drafts" folder (Box 24, Folder 16)
    - "Marigold," TS from Carson's "First Drafts" folder (Box 24, Folder 17)
    - "Nemesis," TS from Carson's "First Drafts" folder (Box 24, Folder 18)
    - "Opium," TS from Carson's "First Drafts" folder (Box 24, Folder 19)
    - "Pegasus," TS from Carson's "First Drafts" folder (Box 24, Folder 20)
    - "Quince," MS and TS from Carson's "First Drafts" folder (Box 24, Folder 21)
    - "Ramification," TS from Carson's "First Drafts" folder (Box 24, Folder 22)
    - "Submarine," TS from Carson's "First Drafts" folder (Box 24, Folder 23)
    - "Tachygraphy," TS from Carson's "First Drafts" folder (Box 24, Folder 24)
    - "Whereabouts," TS from Carson's "First Drafts" folder (Box 24, Folder 25)
    - "Yarn," TS from Carson's "First Drafts" folder (Box 24, Folder 26)
    - "Zoetrope," TS from Carson's "First Drafts" folder (Box 24, Folder 27)
    - Fishing for Amber, "Fair Copy" TS (Box 24, Folder 28)
    - Fishing for Amber, "Second Draft" TS, "Antipodes" to "Io" (Box 24, Folder 29)
    - Fishing for Amber, "Second Draft" TS, "Kipper" to "Xerox" (Box 24, Folder 30)
    - Fishing for Amber, TS, "Berenice" to "Zoetrope" [incomplete] (Box 24, Folder 31)
    - Fishing for Amber, copy editor's queries with TLS from Granta editor 10 May 1999 (Box 25, Folder 1)
    - Fishing for Amber, photocopies of images for chapter title pages (Box 25, Folder 2)
    - Fishing for Amber, proofs of images for chapter title pages (Box 25, Folder 3)
    - Fishing for Amber, proofs from "Antipodes" to "Marigold" [incomplete] (Box 25, Folder 4)
    - Fishing for Amber, proofs from "Nemesis" to "Zoetrope" [incomplete] (Box 25, Folder 5)
    - Fishing for Amber, proofs from "Sources" page (Box 25, Folder 6)
    - Fishing for Amber, jacket sample (Box 25, Folder 7)
    - Shamrock Tea (2001)
    - Shamrock Tea, research materials (Box 25, Folder 8)
    - Shamrock Tea, assorted MS and TS unidentified fragments (Box 25, Folder 9)
    - Shamrock Tea, TS "First (aborted) Version" [21 April 1999] (Box 25, Folder 10)
    - Shamrock Tea, early TS ["Bede," "Caedmon," "Donard"] (Box 25, Folder 11)
    - Shamrock Tea, early TS [title page] (Box 25, Folder 12)
    - Shamrock Tea, early TS, chapters 17, 94 [incomplete] (Box 25, Folder 13)
    - Shamrock Tea, early TS, chapters 1-31 [incomplete] (Box 25, Folder 14)
    - Shamrock Tea, early TS chapters 1-30 [incomplete] (Box 25, Folder 15)
    - Shamrock Tea, early TS chapters 1-39 [incomplete] (Box 25, Folder 16)
    - Shamrock Tea, early TS chapters 28-94 [incomplete] (Box 25, Folder 17)
    - Shamrock Tea, corrected TS [chapters 1-34], with TLS from Carson to Neil Belton, 1 May 2000 (Box 26, Folder 1)
    - Shamrock Tea, corrected TS [chapters 35-68] (Box 26, Folder 2)
    - Shamrock Tea, corrected TS [chapters 69-101] (Box 26, Folder 3)
    - Shamrock Tea, TS with commentaries by Tess Gallagher [chapters 1-24] (Box 26, Folder 4)
    - Shamrock Tea, TS with commentaries by Tess Gallagher [chapters 25-33, 52-75], includes TLS from TG, 21 August 2000 (Box 26, Folder 5)
    - Shamrock Tea, TS with commentaries by Tess Gallagher [chapters 34-49], includes TLS from TG, 19 August 2000 (Box 26, Folder 6)
    - Shamrock Tea, TS with commentaries by Tess Gallagher [chapters 76-89], includes TLS from TG, 22 August 2000 (Box 26, Folder 7)
    - Shamrock Tea, TS with commentaries by Tess Gallagher [chapters 90-101], includes TLS from TG (23 August 2000), CC to TG, CC to Neil Belton (Box 26, Folder 8)
    - Shamrock Tea, corrected TS ["Penultimate Draft"] (Box 26, Folder 9)
    - Shamrock Tea, corrected galley proofs [chapters 1-34] (Box 26, Folder 10)
    - Shamrock Tea, corrected galley proofs [chapters 35-58, 62, 67, 71-74] (Box 26, Folder 11)
    - Shamrock Tea, corrected galley proofs [chapters 76-101] (Box 26, Folder 12)
    - Shamrock Tea, uncorrected galley [bound] (Box 26, Folder 13)
    - Shamrock Tea, blurb by Alberto Manguel (Box 26, Folder 14)
    - Shamrock Tea, sample cover (Box 26, Folder 15)
    - Y and K (circa 2002-2003) [unpublished]
    - Y and K, TS, "New Book (Part One)," 18 May 2002-25 September 2002 (Box 57, Folder 20)
    - Y and K, TS and notes, "Notes/Drafts New Book," September 2002 (Box 57, Folder 21)
    - Y and K, TS and notes, 3 October 2002 (Box 57, Folder 22)
    - Y and K, TS fragments, notes, and research material, 2003 (Box 57, Folder 23)
    - The Pen Friend (2009) [earlier title Under the Green Star]
    - The Pen Friend, research notes, 2003-2005 (Box 57, Folder 24)
    - The Pen Friend, "Under the Green Star," TS with corrections, circa 2004 (Box 57, Folder 25)
    - The Pen Friend, TS with commentary, pages 1-84, June-5 July 2005 (Box 58, Folder 1)
    - The Pen Friend, TS with commentary, pages 85-177, 9 July 2005 (Box 58, Folder 2)
    - The Pen Friend, TS with commentary, pages 179-242, 20 August 2005-2 September 2005 (Box 58, Folder 3)
    - The Pen Friend, "First Fair Copy," TS (Box 58, Folder 4)
    - The Pen Friend, TS, complete draft, circa September 2005 [contains photographs for book] [1 of 2] (Box 58, Folder 5)
    - The Pen Friend, TS, complete draft, circa September 2005 [contains photographs for book] [2 of 2] (Box 58, Folder 6)
    - The Pen Friend, TS, complete draft with copy editor's queries, circa 2005 [1 of 2] (Box 58, Folder 7)
    - The Pen Friend, TS, complete draft with copy editor's queries, circa 2005 [2 of 2] (Box 58, Folder 8)
    - The Pen Friend, TS, complete draft, circa April 2006 (Box 59, Folder 1)
    - The Pen Friend, TS fragments (Box 59, Folder 2)
    - Assorted Prose
    - "The 1940's," TS proof of essay for Watching the River Flow: a Century in Irish Poetry (1999); includes selected poems (Box 27, Folder 1)
    - "Afterword," TS for The Blackbird's Nest, ed. by Frank Ormsby, 2007 (Box 59, Folder 3)
    - "Alter Ego," TS essay for Belfast Frescos (1995) by John Kindness [includes images] (Box 27, Folder 2)
    - "Anonymous," TS essay for Waterstone's Guide to Irish Books [Includes correspondence from editor, 10 April 1998] (Box 27, Folder 3)
    - "Architecture and Music," TS (Box 27, Folder 4)
    - "At the Tomb of Dante Alighieri," TS of performance in Ravenna, Italy, 28 September 2007 [includes Italian translation] (Box 59, Folder 4)
    - "The Bag of Spuds" and "The Telephone Reel," TS of columns in Journal of Music, 2008 (Box 59, Folder 5)
    - "Belfast," TS introduction to reprint of 1923 Ordnance Survey map of Belfast, 5 February 1996 (Box 27, Folder 5)
    - "Belfast: Betwixt, Between, Behind the Name," TS of Chapter Two in Betwixt and Between: Place and Cultural Translation, ed. by Stephen Kelly and David Johnston, 2007 (Box 59, Folder 6)
    - "Belfast Notes," TS of article, for TLS, 18 March 1988 [See also Subseries 4.1: "Belfast Notes," for TLS, 18 March 1988] (Box 27, Folder 6)
    - "Belfast Notes," TS of article, for TLS 24-30 June 1988 [See also Subseries 4.1: "Belfast Notes," 24-30 June 1988] (Box 27, Folder 7)
    - "Belfast Notes," proof of article for TLS, 24-30 June 1988 [See also Subseries 4.1: "Belfast Notes," in TLS, 24-30 June 1988] (Box OP5)
    - "Blurb for a Stor's a Stoirin," TS introduction for Padraigin Ni Uallachain, A Stor's A Stoirin [See Subseries 3.1: Ni Uallachain's A Stor's A Stoirin] (Box -, Folder -)
    - "Brian Ballard Catalogue," TS, 9 March 2005 (Box 59, Folder 7)
    - "Calling It to Mind, Getting It by Heart," TS liner notes for CD of Liam O'Flynn and Seamus Heaney performing together; includes MS notes and TLS from CC [circa 2000-2001] (Box 27, Folder 8)
    - "Clocks Ticking, Tractors Passing," TS (Box 27, Folder 9)
    - "The Dialects of Silence," [review of Ted Mcarthy, Bernard O'Donoghue, Carol Rumens, Aiden Matthews] in Poetry London, summer 1999 (Box 27, Folder 10)
    - "The Drumshanbo Lock-In: Some Reflections on the Rebel Song," TS for The Guardian, 13 August 2002 (Box 27, Folder 11)
    - "Editorial: Thirteen Ways of Looking at a Blackbird," TS (Box 59, Folder 8)
    - "The Floating Crowbar," TS (Box 27, Folder 12)
    - "For All We Know," TS blurb for PBS Choice, Spring 2008 (Box 59, Folder 9)
    - Foreword to Knights of God by Patricia Lynch, TS (Box 59, Folder 10)
    - "From Both Sides of the Track," TS, piece for Calvino anthology edited by Roberto Bertoni, 30 January 2007 (Box 59, Folder 11)
    - Getting Lost, MS notes for essay with ALS from Don Bloch [circa early 2000] (Box 27, Folder 13)
    - "The Horse's Mouth: Some thoughts on translation," TS (Box 59, Folder 12)
    - "House Rules O.K.?" TS (Box 27, Folder 14)
    - "I am coming apart," TS [See Subseries 2.2: Uncollected Poems, "Raftery;" also The New Estate: "The Holiday"] (Box -, Folder -)
    - "IASIL Questionnaire," TS (Box 59, Folder 13)
    - "In the Ear of the Beholder," TS and proof of essay for The Dublin Review (Box 27, Folder 15)
    - "In Praise of the Ceili Band," TS (Box 59, Folder 14)
    - "Inaugural Lecture," TS, for Queen's University Belfast, 5 May 2005 (Box 59, Folder 15)
    - "Introduction" [for Seamus Tansey], TS [circa 1998] (Box 27, Folder 16)
    - "It seems to me that Scotland is not one place, but many," TS for Scotland edition of Sunday Times [1999] (Box 27, Folder 17)
    - "Laces and Eyelets: Reactions to Paul Seawright's Police Force," TS [for Source (Autumn/Winter 1997)] (Box 27, Folder 18)
    - "Living in Troubled Times," TS [variant title: "When Memory Goes Blank"] essay on "September 11, 2001" for Newsday, 7 October 2001 [See also Subseries 4.1: "When Memory Goes Blank"] (Box 27, Folder 19)
    - "Lost and Found," TS of essay for Source, includes photo series responded to (Box 27, Folder 20)
    - "Mick Hoy: An Appreciation," TS, June 2000 (Box 27, Folder 21)
    - "Mountains and Skies," TS for Belfast Review (Box 27, Folder 22)
    - "Mud, Sweat and Beers," TS for A Cultural History of Sport and Alcohol; includes TLS from publisher, 16 May 2002 (Box 27, Folder 23)
    - "On the Road," TS (Box 27, Folder 24)
    - "The Other," TS contribution to Strong Words (2000) (Box 27, Folder 25)
    - "Our Master's Voices," TS for Belfast Review [See also Subseries 4.1: "Our Master's Voices"] (Box 27, Folder 26)
    - "Pamphlet Series," TS (Box 59, Folder 16)
    - "Peg McGrath: A Tribute," TS with faxed note from CC 2 February 1995 (Box 27, Folder 27)
    - "The Perfect Sound and the Dead Man's Breeches," TS (Box 27, Folder 28)
    - "Piece for Harry Bradley," TS (Box 27, Folder 29)
    - "Piece for the Poetry Book Society," TS (Box 27, Folder 30)
    - "Piece for the Poetry Book Society," TS with ALS from Carson to Clare Brown (Box 27, Folder 31)
    - "Recent Irish Architecture," TS [July 2000], with ALS from CC and photocopy of Colm Tóibín's essay "New Irish Architecture" (Box 27, Folder 32)
    - "The Red Hand of Ulster," TS, research material, and proofs, for The Dublin Review, February 2002 (Box 59, Folder 17)
    - "Somebody Up There Listening," TS for Belfast Review [See also Subseries 4.1: "Somebody Up There Listening"] (Box 27, Folder 33)
    - "This Great Estrangement," galley proofs of review of Medbh McGuckian's Shelmalier, spring 1999 (Box 27, Folder 34)
    - "This is what libraries are for," TS and proof [variant title: "The Olfactory File"] (Box 27, Folder 35)
    - "Trains," TS of short story [by Carson?] (Box 59, Folder 18)
    - "An Ulster Ceili," TS of program introduction (Box 27, Folder 36)
    - "The Well," TS introduction for The Well, a program of traditional music and poetry directed by John Comiskey for the Dublin Theatre Festival 2000 [See also Subseries 3.1: The Well] (Box 27, Folder 37)
    - Untitled, TS of chapter in Mortification: Writers' Stories of Their Public Shame, ed. By Robin Robertson, 28 April 2003 (Box 59, Folder 19)
    - Untitled, TS commentary on 1994 T. S. Eliot Prize for Literature awarded to Paul Muldoon [London Daily Telegraph, January 1994] (Box 27, Folder 38)
    - Untitled, TS for Guardian Books of the Year, 2003 (Box 59, Folder 20)
    - Untitled, TS ["I forgot exactly where I had been going"] prose piece on Irish traditional music (Box 27, Folder 39)
    - Untitled, TS ["It's marching time again"] essay on Belfast (Box 27, Folder 40)
    - Untitled, TS ["Maps are another way"] [published title: "West Belfast"] introduction to a reissue of the 1931 Ordnance Survey map of The Falls [See also Peter Fallon/The Gallery Press collection, MS 817, Carson author files, Belfast Confetti, Miscellaneous folder] (Box 27, Folder 41)
    - Untitled Essays and Fragments on Irish Music (Box 27, Folder 42)
    - Unidentified TS fragments (Box 27, Folder 43)
    - Reviews by Carson
    - "Basin and Range," TS and proofs of review of Peter Redgrove and Penelope Shuttle for Poetry London; includes ALS note to Scott Verner, May 2000 (Box 28, Folder 1)
    - "The Basket Weaver's Hands," TS review of All Souls by Michael; Cody (Box 28, Folder 2)
    - "The Crack Goes On," TS review of The Humours of Planxty, for Journal of Music in Ireland by Leagues O'Toole, 5 December 2006 (Box 59, Folder 21)